むった
(六太)＜宇宙飛行士を選ぶ
最終試験のため➡
Eight people are headed to Houston, USA, for the final astronaut selection exam.
アメリカ･ヒューストンに行く
８人｡➡
I managed to worm my way into the last spot.
ひとわく
その最後の一枠に
私は滑り込んだ＞
＜しかし…＞
However...
I will rise,
climb,
and shoot through the atmosphere
My goal is zero gravity
Space Brothers
Waves of people flood the intersection
Like vague silhouettes they stream past incessantly
How do I look in their midst?
I don't know
Hiding my true intentions desperately
I dish out vague excuses
My ambitions of going to space, harbored for so long,
are frail and brittle
No matter how I turn the globus
I have no home where I end up
There's no point to looking on a map
I will rise,
climb,
and shoot through the atmosphere
until I can look down on the entire world
I will yell
and scream
with a heart of steel
that I am going to zero gravity
#23 Father, Son, and Mutta Claus
Dad: forty-five degrees.
Let's eat, everyone!
(南波母)いただきま～す！
Mom: ninety degrees.
Me: twenty-two degrees...
Ah, it went splat.
ああっ パタッて…｡
《私のヒューストン進出祝いの
はずなのに…》
We're supposed to be celebrating my selection for Houston...
ええっ ピタッ…｡
う～ん 美味しい！
Ah, it went plop.
Mmm, delicious!
Congratulations, Mu!
《何故かチョコプレートは
母ちゃんが確保》
But for some reason, Mom ended up with the chocolate tag.
何か…いろいろおかしいよねえ｡
ほら 角度とか｡
Something isn't right here.
If you look at the portion...
(南波父)六太よ…｡
So, Mutta...
Huh?
つまり母さんが
何を言いたいかと言うとだな…➡
Your mother is trying to say that...
your portion of cake represents the load you're carrying.
ケーキの角度は
日頃の働きに比例する！
《やっぱり…
俺が今 無職だからか》
Thought so...
Because I'm still unemployed.
男なら 親父より稼げ！
A son should earn more than his father!
重いわ～ お父さんの言葉！
Your father is so deep!
《くそっ ヒューストンに行くまで
バイトでもするしかねえなあ》
Damn.
I'll have to work a part-time job until I leave for Houston...
ヨッと…ん～｡
バイトつっても 何かねえ｡
Easier said than done...
Christmas Cake Sale!
＜季節は冬…
アルバイト情報誌には やはり➡
It's winter.
Most of the openings are for Christmas positions.
クリスマスがらみの
バイトが多い＞
《だがしかし もしも
こんなバイトをしたら…》
But if I were to take this job...
ケーキいかがっすか～ ケーキ！
ケーキいかがっすか～｡
Would you like a cake?
How about a cake?
わあっ 見て見てたっくん｡
ケーキ マジ ケーキ！
Look, Ta!
They're actually selling cakes!
Yep, there's a candle that looks like a chimney.
ホントだね｡
ろうそくが煙突のようだね｡
どうぞ｡
お兄さんも
素敵なクリスマスを！
Here you go.
I hope you have a wonderful Christmas.
しちゃいかんよな～
こういう仕事は｡
I wouldn't want that job...
＜と思っていたのにも
かかわらず…＞
But in the end...
《どうにか雇ってもらえたのは➡
The job I found was even more Christmasy than selling cakes.
Have Your Picture Taken with Santa
ケーキ売りよりもっと
クリスマスど真ん中な仕事➡
まさにサンタクロース
その人である》
I was Santa Claus himself.
《やるからには
本物のサンタクロースの顔に➡
I wouldn't want to ruin Santa's good name.
泥を塗るわけにはいかない》
I can do this.
《やってやろうじゃねえか
俺はサンタクロースに➡
I will become Santa Claus!
いや ムッタクロースになる！》
No, Mutta Claus!
Ho ho ho, tell me what you want, little girl.
フフフ…願い事を言ってごらん
お嬢ちゃん｡
本物のサンタに会わして｡
I want to see the real Santa.
あ…じゃあ メールしとく｡
Sure, I'll send an e-mail.
Okay!
(ｽﾀｯﾌ)は～い 写真撮りま～す｡
ハイ チーズ！
I'm taking the picture.
And cheese...
はぁ～ 心が痛む｡
Now I feel guilty.
着信ナシ…｡
No new messages.
＜ヒューストン行きの日程が
まだ決まらないのか➡
I assume JAXA hasn't decided when we're leaving for Houston,
ジャクサ
ＪＡＸＡからは連絡がなく
そして…＞
since I haven't heard from them.
And...
《試験に落ちたケンジからも
連絡はない》
I haven't heard from Kenji after he didn't pass.
《私も未だにメールを出せず…》
I can't bring myself to e-mail him...
《やっぱ落ち込んでんのかな
ケンジ…》
Kenji's probably...
feeling down.
あ 今日はお疲れさま 南波君｡
また明日もサンタよろしくね｡➡
Oh, thank you for the hard work, Nanba.
I'll need you back tomorrow, Santa.
はい 今日の分｡
あ ありがとうございます｡
Here's today's pay.
Thank you very much.
《5000円か｡世のサンタは
みんな苦労してんだな》
5,000 yen, huh?
The Santas of the world have it rough.
(手島)久しぶり お父さん｡
Good to see you, Dad.
(手島)メガネ 替えたんだね｡
You changed your glasses.
ゆうり
(手島父)有利…｡
Yuuri.
(手島)やっぱり怒ってる？
お父さん｡
Are you mad, Dad?
(手島父)いや｡
No.
ただ 理解できないだけだ｡
But I don't really understand.
うん｡だから今日 呼んだんだよ｡
That's why I asked you to come over today.
After you've seen my room,
僕の部屋を見てもらえれば
わかってもらえると思ってさ｡
you might understand.
(手島父)これは…｡
This is...
(手島父)作ったのか？これ…｡
Did you make all these?
Yes.
本棚も 父さんの書いた本以外は
ほとんどそっち系か…｡➡
And other than the ones I wrote,
Astronaut
Stories
The Search for
Extraterrestrial
Life
Space
Organisms
A Second
Earth
Life on
Other Planets
most of your books are on the same subject.
有利…➡
Yuuri...
これが お前の理想か｡
Is this what you're looking for?
It's Santa!
フフフ…願い事を言ってごらん
坊や｡
Ho ho ho, tell me what you want, little boy.
ア…アスパラガスを
この世から消して下さい｡
P-Please rid the world of asparagus.
Ah, I understand.
あ なるほど｡
(ｽﾀｯﾌ)は～い 撮ります｡
Okay, ready to take it!
君の願いは きっと叶うよ｡
I'm sure your wish will come true.
Really? Can you also get rid of celery?
(少年)ホント？じゃあセロリも
それからニンジンでしょ➡
And carrots.
ピーマンとかほうれん草
トマトにブロッコリー…｡
Green peppers and spinach...
Tomatoes, broccoli...
《疲れた～ 心が痛む…》
I'm exhausted...
And I still feel guilty.
きたっ!!
This is it!
Hello?
[ｹｲﾀｲ]つるみ
(鶴見)どうも連絡遅くなりました｡
ＪＡＸＡの鶴見です｡
Hello, I apologize for the delay in contacting you.
This is Tsurumi, from JAXA.
ヒューストンへの
日程が決まりました｡
We've chosen the date for your departure to Houston.
はい…はい！
了解しました｡
Yes.
I understand.
それでは また｡
[ｹｲﾀｲ]あ あの～ 鶴見さん！
Goodbye.
U-Uh, Tsurumi...
はい？
ケンジは…➡
Yes?
About Kenji...
まかべ
真壁君は 何で
選ばれなかったんですか？
Why wasn't Makabe selected?
[ｹｲﾀｲ]僕が残されたのに
彼が残らないっていうのは➡
It doesn't feel right that I was chosen, but he wasn't.
何かこう不自然で…➡
きっとケンジも
そう思ってるんじゃないかと｡
I'm sure he feels the same way.
君達は 何というか
いいコンビだな｡➡
The two of you are good friends.
そういう仲間意識の強さが
君達は評価されたんだ｡
The committee was impressed by the bond you share.
真壁君も 君とまったく同じことを
聞いてきたよ｡
[ｹｲﾀｲ]ええっ!?
Makabe asked me the exact same question.
Huh?
ちゃんと選ばれてるよ 真壁君も｡
Makabe was chosen, as well.
南波君 今日まで
お疲れさまでした｡
お世話になりました｡
Nanba, thanks for everything.
Thank you.
(鶴見)⦅真壁君も同じ勘違いを
してたみたいだね｡➡
Makabe also made the wrong assumption.
発表が８人だったから⦆
Because we announced that eight had been selected.
⦅本当はね ９人いたんだよ⦆
Actually, we chose nine people.
⦅発表前に１人辞退したんだ⦆
But one withdrew before the announcement.
成績で見れば
Ｂ班で一番優秀だった男がね…｡
Based on their scores,
he was Team B's best candidate.
⦅本当にすみませんでした⦆
I'm very sorry.
⦅あの時 受験免責書類に
サインする時にも➡
At the beginning of the exam,
最後まで迷ったんですが➡
I hesitated to sign the form.
結局 まわりの流れに乗ってしまう
タチが出てしまって…⦆
But I ended up just going with the flow.
⦅意外だな｡君はてっきり➡
This is a surprise.
I thought that you wanted to carry on your father's dream.
お父さんの意思を継ぐものだと
思っていたよ⦆
なすだ
(茄子田)⦅ねえ｡３回もねえ➡
Yes, since your father participated in the astronaut selection exam on three occasions.
宇宙飛行士選抜受けた人だもんね
君のお父さん⦆
(手島)⦅はい｡ご存知のとおり
厳格な人でして➡
Yes...
As I'm sure you know, he's a strict person.
僕も父の望むとおり
宇宙飛行士になるんだって➡
I told myself that I wanted to be an astronaut,
just as my father wanted.
自分に言い聞かせてました｡
だけど…➡
But...
真壁君たちと
地球外生命の話をした時に➡
When I was talking to Makabe and everyone else about extraterrestrial life,
自分は やっぱりこっちだって
思ったんです⦆
I realized that this was my true calling.
⦅じゃあ何で 最後にあんなに
頑張って成績を上げたんだい？➡
Then why work so hard to raise your scores toward the end?
You could have stopped trying.
引いてもよかったんじゃ
ないのか？⦆
⦅ええ あれは選ばれたくて必死に
なったわけじゃなくて…➡
Yeah, I wasn't working so hard to be chosen.
ここでもし
一番になれたとしたら➡
I thought that if I were the best candidate here,
何だってやれると
思ったからです⦆
I could do whatever I wanted.
⦅うん そうだね｡
何だってやれるね 君なら｡➡
Yes, that's true.
You can do whatever you want.
さよなら…⦆
Goodbye.
有利…本当にいると
思っているのか？➡
Yuuri.
Do you truly believe they exist?
お前の部屋にあった
あんな生き物が｡
That those organisms in your room are real?
あれは あくまで想像だけど
必ずいるって信じてるよ｡➡
Those are products of my imagination,
but I believe that life is out there.
ＪＡＸＡの宇宙科学研究本部が
アメリカのＪＰＬと共同で➡
JAXA's ISAS is working with JPL in the US to send a third probe to Europa.
エウロパに３機目の探査機を
送る計画を進めてるんだ｡➡
一番氷の薄いところから
進入して➡
They plan to enter where the ice is thinnest,
海中の生態系を探査する
凄い計画なんだ｡➡
to investigate life in the water.
史上初の地球外生物の発見になる
かもしれない！
We may discover our first extraterrestrial life form!
僕もそれに加わりたくてさ
明日 面接を受けることになった｡
I want to join that project.
I have an interview tomorrow.
(手島父)じゃあ 大学の講師も
辞めるんだな？
Then you'll stop lecturing at the university?
(手島)うん…ごめん｡
Yes, I'm sorry.
⦅父の期待を裏切ることが
ずっと怖かったんですが➡
I was always afraid of going against my father's expectations.
今 ようやく気づきました｡僕は
自分の父には 逆らえますが➡
But then I finally understood.
I could bring myself to defy my father,
自分のやりたいことには
逆らえません！⦆
but I could never defy my own dreams.
Yuuri...
(手島父)有利 お前の名前は
史上初めて 宇宙へ行った➡
I named you after the first man in space,
飛行士 ユーリ･ガガーリンから
とった｡
Yuri Gagarin.
父さんの気持ちも
わかるだろう？
Can you understand what I hoped for you?
もしいつか 有利の手で
史上初の地球外生物を➡
If you discover
the first extraterrestrial life form,
発見できたら…そいつに 有利
お前の名前をつけてやれ！
name it "Yuuri", after your own name.
(手島父)じゃあ またな｡
明日の面接 頑張れ｡
Then, I'll see you later.
Good luck on your interview tomorrow.
Yes.
May 26
Breakfast: two bowls natto rice,
miso soup with radish and seaweed,
boiled greens and spinach,
egg on rice.
Apple and banana for dessert.
なっとうごはん ２杯 たこ焼き
お好み焼き りんごあめ…｡
Two bowls of natto rice...
August 7
We all went to a local summer festival.
Takoyaki, okonomiyaki, delicious! Can't forget
the candy apple! The corn on the cob and
shaved ice were also good.
Takoyaki, okonomiyaki, candy apple...
あ～ こうやって見ると
食べ物ネタばっかりだな➡
Looking back,
I spent the whole year writing about food again.
今年も まあいいや｡
Oh, well...
お父さん！これ 今年の日記｡
読んどいてね｡
Dad, here's my diary for the past year.
Read it for me.
I'll come back for it later.
今度また 取りにくるから｡
今年は いろんな人に
出会ったよ お父さん｡
I met a lot of people this year, Dad.
Furuya
Fukuda
Nanba
Nitta
似顔絵も 描いといたからね｡
I drew pictures of them.
Serika, could you start a journal?
(せりか父)⦅せりか 日記を
書いてくれないか？➡
父さん ちょっと
入院が長引きそうなんだ｡➡
It looks like I'll be in the hospital for a while.
退院するまでの間で いいからさ⦆
It's just for while I'm stuck here.
⦅せりかにとって 毎日が
どんな日だったのか➡
I want to know what's going on with you every day.
それだけ 知りたいんだよ⦆
⦅わかった｡じゃあ
退院するまで書くね⦆
Okay,
I'll keep a diary while you're in the hospital.
たいやき ２個ください！
１個は カスタードで｡
(店主)はいよっ！
Two taiyaki, please.
One with custard.
Sure.
う～ん！ウフフ…｡
ふうか
(風佳)ギャー!!うわ～ん…｡
Ah! Come on, Fuuka!
(ユキ)あ～ こら風佳！
走らないの！
Stop running!
いや～!!
すげえなぁ パワーが｡
She's a powerful kid.
言うことを聞かない時は
いつも こんな感じなんだよ｡
This is what happens when she doesn't want to listen.
Come on!
(ユキ)こらっ！
うぇ～ん！ギャー！
Oh, she went into hiding.
《あ…隠れた》
(ユキ)フーちゃん 自分でこぼした
牛乳 ちゃんと拭きなさい！
Fu, clean up the milk you spilled.
(風佳)いや～！キャー！
じゃあ ムッ君を
駅まで送ってくる｡
Well, I'm walking Mu to the station.
(ユキ)あ はい！
おじゃましました！
Right.
Thanks for having me over.
It was nothing.
Daddy, roo-ra!
パパー かぺ～！
There it is!
あ 出た！かぺ｡
アハハ！
パパは すぐ帰ってくるよ｡
ムッ君に言ってあげなよ｡
I'll be right back.
Wish Mu good luck.
ムック かぺ～！ヒヒッ…｡
Mumu, roo-ra!
ん～！ありがとう フーちゃん！
うれしいな～｡
Thanks, Fu. I'm so happy...
ムックは 別の生き物だけど…｡
But Mumu is someone totally different.
よ～し やる気出てきた！
かぺるよ 俺！➡
Okay, I'm fired up!
Time to roo-ra it up!
ガチャピンに 勝つ！
I will beat Gachapin!
とは 言ってみたもののね…
サンタ以降 な～んも➡
Having said all that...
I haven't done any work after that Santa job.
仕事してないんだよ 俺｡
あ～ 金は減る一方だし➡
I'm running out of money,
ケーキとかピザの角度は
どんどん鋭利になっていくよ｡
and my pizza and cake slices are shrinking daily.
食べやすくて いいじゃん｡
Then they're easier to eat.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](鶴見)
ﾋｭｰｽﾄﾝへの日程が決まりました｡
We've chosen the date for your departure to Houston.
＜最終試験が
２ヶ月後ということが分かり➡
After hearing that the final exam would be in two months,
私は みんなより先に
ヒューストンへ行くことにした｡➡
I went to Houston ahead of schedule.
アポの面倒でも見ながら
どうせなら➡
I figured I could take care of Apo,
and tour the Johnson Space Center at the same time.
ジョンソンスペースセンターを
見学しつくしてやろうと➡
考えたのだ｡最終試験は
なぜ２ヶ月後なのか？➡
Why were they waiting two months for the final exam?
それは ＪＡＸＡの
いき
はか
粋な計らいだった＞
That was JAXA being sympathetic.
ひびと
セス
＜日々人達 ＣＥＳ－５１
クルーの打ち上げに➡
They timed the exam to coincide with when Hibito and the other CES-51 members would be lifting off.
日程を合わせてくれたのだ｡
みんなで 打ち上げを➡
That way, we could all watch the launch.
見られるように と＞
兄の六太君もいることだし
せっかく アメリカまで➡
The director thought it would be appropriate,
given that the older brother would be in America.
行くんだからって
理事長がね｡
え…そうなんですか｡
Really?
《優しいなぁ 理事長｡
優しいなぁ ＪＡＸＡ》
The director's so nice.
JAXA's so nice.
Really...
《ほんと…余計なこと
しやがって！➡
I didn't want that at all!
Just think about it!
考えてみろ！みんなと一緒に
打ち上げを見るということは➡
If we watch the launch together,
みんなに 見られるわけだよ！》
they'll all be looking at me!
《弟に 完全に先を越されて
しまった瞬間ホヤホヤの➡
They'll witness the older brother's lackluster reaction, as his younger brother passes him by.
兄の 何ともビミョーな顔を》
ムッ君 なに その顔？
Mu, what's with that look on your face?
え!?あ～ いや別に…｡
Oh, it's nothing.
じゃあな ケンジ｡
ヒューストンで待ってるぜ｡
So long, Kenji.
I'll be waiting for you in Houston.
うん｡また！
Yep, until then.
Oh, I forgot.
っと 忘れてた！
かぺ！
Roo-ra.
Both of us could tell
＜私達は 気づいていた｡我々が
宇宙飛行士に近づく度に➡
that our handshakes were growing stronger,
２人の握手も だんだん
力強くなってきてるのを＞
as we drew closer to achieving our dreams.
たっしゃ
達者でな！
Take care of yourself.
Remaining Balance                                            20 yen
ちょっと チャ…チャージをね｡
I need to ch-charge my card...
《♪～ ＮＡＳＡが
俺を呼んでいる➡
NASA is calling to me!
ＮＡＳＡが
俺を呼んでいる》
フフッ…フッ｡
アポ！久しぶりじゃねえか！
Apo, I haven't seen you in a while.
See?
(日々人)ほ～らね！ムッちゃんは
ちゃんと選ばれて➡
I knew you'd be back after you were selected.
また ここに戻ってくるって
俺の言った通りになったろ｡
I was right.
日々人…そんなこと
言ってたっけ お前？
Hibito...
I don't remember you saying that.
あれ 言ってなかった!?
Huh? Didn't I?
Darn, I never said it aloud.
《しまった…思ってただけか》
それより 今回も 母ちゃんから
お土産があるぞ！
Anyway, I have another present from Mom.
まさか 賞味期限ギリギリの
キムチとか？
More kimchi that's about to expire?
フン…｡
イエス！
Yes!
The lens inside my eyes
went completely out of focus when I saw you
The signs of love flooded the occipital lobe of my cerebrum
The words the left side of my brain produced
brought my vocal cords to reverberation
Vigorously my confession traversed my tongue
May I love you?
May I really love you?
May I be beside you? (The concentration of my hormones rose)
(Dopamine overwhelmed me)
Can I hold your hand? (My blood circulation powered up)
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#24 The Worst
Possible Interviewer
＜ついに私は宇宙飛行士の
最終試験のためアメリカへ＞
I'm in America for the final selection exam!
But some horrible news greeted me.
＜そこで私を待ち受けていたのは
とんでもない知らせだった＞
Just to warn you, your final exam will be especially difficult.
＜言っとくけど あんたにとっては
最終試験が一番の難関よ｡➡
審査員に アズマがいるからね＞
Because Azuma is one of the interviewers.
Azuma, a veteran astronaut, was said to be jealous of Hibito being the first Japanese person on the moon!
あづま
＜先輩宇宙飛行士の吾妻さんは
日本人として最初に月に立つ➡
日々人のことを
ねた
妬んでいるという＞
And he's interviewing me.
＜そんな人に
審査されるなんて！＞
Next time on Space Brothers:
"The Worst Possible Interviewer!"
My luck is so terrible!
＜どこまでついてないんだ 俺は＞
パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
We captured "Kounotori"!
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真です！
すっげえ！
Awesome!